Guide to the People's Educational Society and Camp Tamiment Records TAM.007.003
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
People's Educational Camp Society and Camp Tamiment Records
1920-1972
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
People's Educational Camp Society
TAM.007.003
4.75 Linear Feet (10 boxes)
The People's Educational Camp Society (PECS) owned and operated Camp Tamiment, an educational and recreational summer resort (originally) for socialists and their families near Bushkill, Pa., from 1920 until its sale in 1965 to commercial interests. Camp revenues helped support the Rand School of Social Science and other progressive organizations. Camp Tamiment's success led to the revoking of PECS' tax exempt status in 1963. In 1972 PECS became the Tamiment Institute, thus taking the name of, and becoming identical with its subsidiary, founded in 1935 as the educational arm of Camp Tamiment. This collection contains minutes, correspondence, documents pertaining to PECS' tax status, brochures, programs, announcements and a brief history of the camp and the Tamiment Institute.
Custodial History
The People's Educational Camp Society and Camp Tamiment records were transferred to New York University in 1963 by the People's Educational Camp Society (later renamed the Tamiment Institute), as part of a larger transfer of records of the Rand School of Social Science and of organizations associated with the founding and maintenance of the School (including the American Socialist Society, The Society of the Commonwealth Center, and the People's Educational Camp Society) as well as the contents of the School's library, the Meyer London Memorial Library.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
The People's Educational Camp Society (PECS), incorporated in New York in 1920, owned and operated Camp Tamiment, an educational and recreational summer resort (originally) for socialists and their families near Bushkill, Pa., until its sale in 1965 to commercial interests. As envisioned by its founders, members of the American Socialist Society, the Rand School's governing body, Camp Tamiment revenues helped support the Rand School and other progressive organizations, and provided the majority of the Rand School's funds between 1937 and 1956. In 1951, PECS took title to People's House, the home of the Rand School, and in 1956 the the title to the Rand School was transferred to PECS from the American Socialist Society. Camp Tamiment's success as a recreational resort under managing director Ben Josephson came to overshadow its educational activities, in the opinion of the Internal Revenue Service, which revoked the tax exempt status of PECS in 1963. This action contributed to the decision, later that year, to donate the Tamiment Institute Library (formerly the Meyer London Memorial Library of the Rand School), to New York University. On September 11, 1972, PECS became the Tamiment Institute, thus taking the name of, and becoming identical with, its subsidiary which was founded in 1935 as the educational arm of Camp Tamiment, and which later administered the Tamiment Institute Library for PECS from 1957 to 1963.
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains minutes of the board of directors (1920-1968) and membership meetings; articles of incorporation and by-laws; reports, including those of the managing directors (including Ben Josephson) and educational directors of the Camp; correspondence, including that of Bertha Mailly, first director of the camp, of board chair Stephen C. Vladeck, and also correspondence with the Rand School of Social Science; documents pertaining to the PECS tax case; financial records; brochures, programs, announcements and a brief history of the camp and Tamiment Institute.
Arrangement
The folders in each series are arranged alphabetically.
Organized into three series:
Missing Title
1. Incorporation and Minutes
2. PECS Tax Case and Camp Tamiment History and Activities
3. Addendum
Related Material at the New York University Archives
Tamiment Institute Records (TAM 007.004)
Tamiment Playhouse Records (TAM 107)
Tamiment Playhouse Photographs (Photographs 41)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by the People's Educational Camp Society, 1963. The accession number associated with this gift is 1963.007.
A Camp Tamiment Schedule of Rates was found in repository in April of 2014 and added to this collection. The accession number associated with this material is 2014.057.
Socialism -- United States.; Adult education -- United States.; Correspondence.; Brochures.; Annual reports.; Bushkill (Pa.); Camps -- Pennsylvania; Minutes (administrative records); Oral histories (literary works); Rand School of Social Science; Camp Tamiment (Pa.); People's Educational Camp Society; Mailly, Bertha Howell; Josephson, Ben, 1895-1980; Vladeck, Stephen C.; People's Educational Camp Society
- Series I: Incorporation and Minutes.
  - Box and Folder List; item level lists for minutes and reports folders, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - American Socialist Society: Certificate of Incorporation [Copy], 1901 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Annual Report of the Managing Director of Camp Tamiment, 1925-1959 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Application for Loan on Second Mortgage upon Camp Tamiment, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Board of Directors- Correspondence, Jan 3, 1920-1929 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Board of Directors- Correspondence, 1930-1961 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Board of Directors- Educational Committee Minutes, Oct 22, 1951-Jan 24, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Board of Directors- Joint Educational Committee (w. Rand School) Minutes, Dec 8, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Board of Directors- Joint Negotiations Committee Minutes, Feb 21, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Board of Directors- Members List, 1944-1969 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Board of Directors- Minutes, Dec 15, 1920-Dec 31, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Board of Directors- Minutes, Jan 6, 1922-Sep 22, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Board of Directors- Minutes, Oct 13, 1925-Dec 18, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Board of Directors- Minutes, Jan 8, 1929-Dec 23, 1931 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Board of Directors- Minutes, Jan 6, 1932-Dec 21, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Board of Directors- Minutes, Apr 9, 1935-Sep 10, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Board of Directors- Minutes, Oct 9, 1939-1941 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Board of Directors- Minutes, Jan 19, 1942-Dec 23, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Board of Directors- Minutes, 1945-1949 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Board of Directors- Minutes, 1950-1954 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Board of Directors- Minutes, 1955-1959 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Board of Directors- Minutes, 1960-1965 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Board of Directors- Minutes: Membership Meetings, 1942-1965 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Board of Directors- Memoranda, Misc. Reports, 1928-1953 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Board of Directors- Population Graphs, 1923-1932 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Board of Directors- Publications "At Fifty: two profiles of Ben Josephson", 1945 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - By Laws, 1920 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Certificate of Authority, Pennsylvania, May 6, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Certificate of Incorporation, NY, Dec 6, 1920 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Costack, Ada: Last Will and Testament [$10.000 to Rand School], 1917 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Lee, Algernon: Letter to the Lusk Committee, Jun 6, 1919 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Mailly, Bertha: Letter to Bank of Manhattan (re: Lusk Committee), Jul 14, 1919 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - New York Call Certificate of Incorporation [copy], 1919 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - New York Call Certificate of Increase in Capital Stock, 1919 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Rand Educational Institute: Certificate of Incorporation, Mar 11, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Report of the Head Counselor of Camp Sandyville, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Reports of the Education Director of Camp Tamiment, 1955-1962 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - United States of America vs. Scott Nearing and the American Socialist Society, 1918 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - West, Ilona: Letter to Bertha Mailly, Agreeing to Loan Debs Portrait to Rand School, Jun 2, 1918 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Series II: PECS Tax Case and Camp Tamiment History and Activities.
  - Activities- Correspondence re: Camp Tamiment Forum, Aug 10, 1945 -Sep 24, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Apfel & Englander, CPAs- re: tax case, 1953-1959 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Camp Tamiment Activities, 1920-1964 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Camp Tamiment Building Plans (Oversize), undated (Flat-file-folder 3)
  - Camp Tamiment History typescripts, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Tax Case- Miscellaneous, 1936-1954 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Tax Return- Form 990 (IRS) FY, 1940-1955 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - U.S. Tax Court Case Decision- Docket # 82223, Feb 12, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Waldman and Waldman, Attorneys re: tax case, 1950-1954 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Series III. Addendum.
  - PECS Apfelt Englander CPAs, 1954-1964-1964 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - PECS Board of Directors Bond Issuance Contract ($50,000), Oct 19, 1931 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - PECS Board of Directors Election, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - PECS Bond Issuance Contract ($80,000) with Stroudsburg Security Trust Company, Apr 1, 1942 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - PECS Bond Issuing Contract ($60,000), 1926 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - PECS Bonds, First and Second Mortgage, etc., Apr 1905-1958 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - PECS By-Laws, undated (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - PECS Camp Tamiment: Blaker Ben, May 1905-1963 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - PECS Camp Tamiment: Board of Directors Correspondence, Apr 1905-1945 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Camp Tamiment Schedule of Rates, 1929 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - PECS Camp Tamiment: Board of Directors Correspondence, Apr 1905-1947 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - PECS Camp Tamiment: Board of Directors Correspondence, 1948-1952 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - PECS Camp Tamiment: Board of Directors Correspondence, 1953-1955 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - PECS Camp Tamiment: Board of Directors Correspondence, 1954-1962 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - PECS Camp Tamiment: Board of Directors Correspondence: Re Meetings By Laws, Nov, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - PECS Camp Tamiment: Brochures, 1922 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - PECS Camp Tamiment: Brochures, 1930-1939 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - PECS Camp Tamiment: Brochures, 1940-1949 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - PECS Camp Tamiment: Brochures, 1950-1959 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - PECS Camp Tamiment: Brochures, 1960-1969 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - PECS Camp Tamiment: Brochures (Repros), 1921-1932 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - PECS Camp Tamiment: Brochures (Repros), 1933-1939 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - PECS Camp Tamiment: Correspondence, 1948-1956 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - PECS Camp Tamiment Post-1965 History, 1965-1986 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - PECS Camp Tamiment: Property Deeds, 1920 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - PECS Camp Tamiment: Property Deeds, 1965-1969 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - PECS Certificate of Incorporation, 1956 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - PECS Certificate of Incorporation: Amended, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - PECS Correspondence, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - PECS Correspondence, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - PECS Correspondence, 1970-1972 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - PECS Correspondence re Pennsylvania Tax Matters, 1935 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - PECS Debenture Bonds, Correspondence, 1930-1939 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - PECS Debenture Bonds, Schedule of, 1928 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - PECS Financial Reports (annual), 1948-1955 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - PECS Financial Reports (annual), 1956-1965 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - PECS ILGWU: Sale of Land to PECS for 1$, 1928 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - PECS IRS Tax: Protests Against Ruling Revoking…, 1954-1965 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - PECS Kurt Wagner, Captain of Waiters v. Camp Tamiment [Small Claims Court], 1957 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - PECS: Lectures and Concerts, 1955-1956 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - PECS: Membership / Dues, 1970 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - PECS: Miscellaneous, 1965-1975 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - PECS: New York Call Articles re Camp Tamiment, 1920-1922 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - PECS New York University, 1967 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - PECS Rand School Bookkeeping Records; Reorganization Committee, 1951-1952 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - PECS Rand School Correspondence, 1953-1956 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - PECS Rand School Reports and Related Items, 1947-1954 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - PECS Re Estate of Algernon Lee, 1954 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - PECS Retirement Plan, undated (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - PECS Sandyville: Tenants, etc., 1952-1960 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - PECS Smith, Philomen H. Donation of Land to PECS, 1946 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - PECS Society of The Commonwealth Center, 1933-1956 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - PECS Tamiment Ad, Brochures / Conventions, Meetings, 1960-1962 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - PECS Tamiment Institute Events, 1947-1956 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - PECS Tamiment Institute, Name change to, Jul 5, 1972 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - PECS Tax Exemption Application, 1966 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - PECS Unity House (ILGWU), 1951-1954 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - PECS: Vladeck, Stephen C.: Board of Directors Minutes, Notes, Correspondence, 1960-1963 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - PECS: Vladeck, Stephen C.: Board of Directors Minutes, Notes, Correspondence, 1963-1965 (Box 9, Folder 10)